<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rome's overthrow in a fatal blow at her greatest idol, which leaves all inexusable who resolve still to be blind after such plain conviction a discourse very seasonable for these times wherein popery doth daily threaten in the nation / by a son of the Church.</title>
            <author>Son of the Church.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57614</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29335</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11076834</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11076834</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57614)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1431:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rome's overthrow in a fatal blow at her greatest idol, which leaves all inexusable who resolve still to be blind after such plain conviction a discourse very seasonable for these times wherein popery doth daily threaten in the nation / by a son of the Church.</title>
                  <author>Son of the Church.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Kidgell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Transubstantiation.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46261:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46261:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome's Overthrow,</hi> IN A FATAL BLOW AT HER GREATEST IDOL: Which leaves all Inexcuſable who reſolve ſtill to be Blind after ſuch plain Conviction.</p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Very Seaſonable for theſe Times, wherein <hi>POPERY</hi> Doth daily threaten Prevalence in the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Son of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Kidgell</hi> at the <hi>Atlas</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:46261:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46261:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ROME'S OVER THROW, In a FATAL BLOW At her GREATEST IDOL, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas when <hi>Popery</hi> hath prevailed in <hi>England,</hi> the ſoreſt ſtroke which fell on the ſincere <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> was for their confeſſing againſt their moſt Idolized <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and on the conſideration of the danger of its return, and conſequently the need we have of being fortified againſt their Principles, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally their Magick of Tranſubſtantiation, I would herein endeavour to lay open its firſt Invention, as alſo to Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomize and Confute it.</p>
            <p>Wheras the People of <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Infidel Rome,</hi> being not content with the <hi>Pompilian</hi> Inſtitution in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of little round Loaves; but that the <hi>Roman</hi> Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Pontifes muſt needs further ordain the Kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and immolating of Beaſts, that they might eat, and communicate of the Fleſh of Victims in their Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, eſpecially the Sheep, the Sow, the Goat, and the Oxe, which was firſt inſtituted by <hi>Evander</hi> King of <hi>Arcadia:</hi> Wherefore, that the <hi>Miſſalians</hi> might not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46261:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>degenerate from the Idolatry of their Predeceſſors, they muſt needs follow this communion of fleſh: And they not content with their little round Azimal Hoſts, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, and printed with Images, but with time they have invented a new Magick to tranſubſtantiate their little Hoſts of Flower, into Fleſh and Bones, the bread being no more bread but an accident without ſubſtance; and by this means to convert the round Hoſt of flower into a Carnal and Sanguinolent Hoſt.</p>
            <p>The Wine alſo offered in their Miſſal Chalices to be tranſubſtantiated into Blood, the Wine being no more Wine, but an Accident without Subſtance.</p>
            <p>Was there ever a more abominable Magick, or a more deteſtable Hereſie than this Miſſaline Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation? When the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> murmured againſt God, becauſe they were weary of Eating Manna and celeſtial Bread, calling for fleſh, was the Manna tranſubſtantiated into Feſh, Bones and Blood? When the ancient <hi>Roman</hi> Idolaters meant to change their round Hoſt of Flower or Meal, and grew to eat Fleſh in their ſacrifices, did they uſe this Magick of Tranſubſtantiation? Wherefore I freely averr, that this Miſſal Addition was lately invented by the <hi>Miſſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> more than a Thouſand years after the Incarnation of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This Hereſie began to ſpread very much by a <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laitane</hi> Antichriſt, climbing up to the <hi>Roman</hi> Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy; by the monopoly and ſuggeſtions of <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> expelling by force the other elected Pope, which was <hi>Benedict</hi> the ſecond of that name, in the year of Jeſus Chriſt 1062.</p>
            <p>Afterwards by a Monopoly held in St. <hi>John Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> it was advanced during the Eclefiaſtical Tyranny of <hi>Innocent</hi> the III. of that name, about Two
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46261:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>hundred years after the <hi>Palinodie</hi> canonized by <hi>Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius</hi> Dean of St. <hi>Maurice</hi> in <hi>Angiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt which abominable Magick and Hereſie we muſt briefly by form of a Recapitulation compare the Inſtitutions of the Sacraments ordained by God.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, the Fruits of the knowledge of good and ill, forbidden to our firſt Father <hi>Adam</hi> as ſacred Signs and Sacraments of Fear and Obedience, whereon depended Life or Death, were they tranſubſtantiated or converted into Knowledge or into Death; to leave their nature of being Trees or Fruits, reduced to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident without ſubſtance?</p>
            <p>The celeſtial Manna, and the Rock guſhing out lively water, Sacraments that had reference to the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Supper, were they tranſubſtantiated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an accident without ſubſtance?</p>
            <p>The unſpotted Lambs immolated by <hi>Abel,</hi> in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Sacrifice to God, were they tranſubſtantiated into another nature?</p>
            <p>The Fore-skin circumciſed, for a note and mark of Covenant to the good Patriarch <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, was it converted into an accident without ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance?</p>
            <p>The Blood of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> for an aſſurance of <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſalvation, was that converted into any other ſubſtance?</p>
            <p>The Fleſh of the immaculate Lamb, to be eaten on the day of the Paſſover, having reference to the holy Sacrament of the Supper, was it tranſubſtantiated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an accident without ſubſtance?</p>
            <p>The brazen Serpent, which being only beheld, Health was granted to the Sick, did it not continue a Serpent of Braſs? was that tranſubſtantiated, being ordained for a Sacrament and ſacred ſign to the People of <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:46261:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Victims offered in Sacrifice, both of Beaſts of the Earth, and Azimal Loaves, with other ſacred Signs or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God, for holy Signs and Sacraments of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piation and Salvation for the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were they ever tranſubſtantiated into accidents without ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance?</p>
            <p>All ſacred Signs ordained by God in the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> Church, though they Sacramentally repreſented that which was by them figured, and not as a ſimple Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture without real effect, yet did there never live ſo deteſtable an Heretick, which invented or added there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto this Magick of Tranſubſtantiation; And never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, <hi>O Papiſts,</hi> you muſt needs confeſs that the good and holy Fathers of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were adopted, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted, and regenerated by Faith in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that they were nouriſhed, and obtained Eternal Life by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that they and we have but one God, and one only Jeſus Chriſt, one Mediator and Redeemer; that by Faith, they Sacramentally communicated, and participated ſpiritually of the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, for their ſalvation and eternal Life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference touching God, between them who did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede the Incarnation of Jeſus Chriſt, and us that were ſince his Incarnation:But both they and we are equally the Church of God, redeemed by the blood of the Juſt and unſpotted Lamb Chriſt Jeſus. For the reſt, they had a Faith of the future Promiſe, and obſerved the holy Sacraments and ſacred Symbols of the Sacrifice which ſhould be conſummated by Chriſt Jeſus; and we in the New Law celebrate the Memorial and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Sacrifice now finiſhed by Jeſus Chriſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a fruition of the Promiſe accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>If then the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> eat the ſame celeſtial Bread, and drank the ſame ſaving drink which we do by Faith in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46261:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>one onely Jeſus Chriſt; if they had ſacred ſigns to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent actually and really the future death of Jeſus Chriſt, even as we retain ſacred ſigns of his preſent or paſt death; they for the future, and we for what is paſt; why did the Papiſts invent this new Magick, to convert an holy Sacrament ordained by God, into a Magick of Tranſubſtantiation, and into an accident without ſubſtance? If God to approve his power, and to manifeſt the hardneſs and obſtinacy of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> was pleaſed to perform wonderful things by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> by converting a Rod into a Serpent, Water of the River into Blood, and into Frogs; and duſt of the Earth into Lice; and then to make the Navigable Sea dry, performing many other Miracles; can we by this inferr a Tranſubſtantiation of the little round azimal Hoſt, printed with Images, into an accident without a ſubſtance? In what place of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, when mention is made of ſacred Signs and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, or Sacrifices Ordained by God, is it ſaid that the Sign or Sacrament was tranſubſtantiated? But on the contrary, Gods will, accommodating it ſelf to mans Infirmity, he ordained from time to time common ſigns, for notes and marks of aſſurance of the thing ſignified: wherein Gods power is the more renowned and exalted, in really giving us what by the ſacred ſign is repreſented, by the virtue of Faith, and of the Holy Ghoſt, as if the Sign it ſelf had been really tranſubſtantiated by ſome ocular Miracle. For the Sacraments comprehend in them, more ſpiritual than carnal ſenſe. For this reaſon God by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ever blamed his People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sacraments too carnally.</p>
            <p>But tell me, ye <hi>Papiſts,</hi> when <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> made it known how he was the true Bread of Life deſcended
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46261:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>from Heaven, to conferre Life Eternal; and how theſe ſacramental words of eating his Fleſh, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Blood, were to be underſtood, wherewith the <hi>Capernaites</hi> your Predeceſſors were offended; did he teach us in this Interpretation, that to eat his Fleſh ſhould be meant, by a little round tranſubſtantiated Hoſt? That the round Hoſt of Flower and the Wine, is no more Bread or Wine, but Accidents without Subſtance? Is this your abominable Magick the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Jeſus Chriſt? Nothing leſs. But Jeſus Chriſt like a true and heavenly Law-giver, who can only ſincerely interpret his own Law, made anſwer to the <hi>Capernaite</hi> Doctors, how they were groſs and carnal minded, minding only the Fleſh, as you Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts doe, though the Fleſh alone profits nothing; alleadging how his ſacramental words were ſpiritual: <hi>The Fleſh,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>profits not; but the Spirit quickens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo, <hi>O Papiſts,</hi> how can you religiouſly accord your Tranſubſtantiation with the Doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt, which promiſeth and aſſureth <hi>Eternal Life</hi> to thoſe that ſhall eat his Fleſh and drink his Blood, if you conceive theſe words carnally? For you cannot be ignorant but that your own Bodies when they have devoured theſe round tranſubſtantiated Hoſts into Fleſh and Bones, drunk and taken down the tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated Wine into Blood, notwitſtanding live, and are mortal through the neceſſity of the Law. Wherefore, Eternal Life promiſed by this Communion, cannot be underſtood by a mortal Body, or Fleſh. And therefore of neceſſity you muſt needs acknowledge, for the moſt ſacred Interpretation, that to eat the Body and drink the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, muſt have reference to a ſpiritual and heavenly Life; and that the <hi>fleſh profits nothing,</hi> but the ſpiritual words; and the Communion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46261:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, by Faith and Spirit give Eternal Life. This Interpretation is many times recited by the holy Apoſtle St. <hi>John:</hi> when Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt himſelf uſeth theſe words, <hi>He that comes to me, ſhall never hunger; he that helieves in me ſhall never thirſt, but haave Eternal Life;</hi> are not theſe terms intelligible enough, to expreſs this holy Sacrament of the Communion of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, without running to your Magick of Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            <p>Another Interpretation of the holy Doctor and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Sacramental Law is deſcribed, when Jeſus Chriſt was interrogated by <hi>Nchodemus,</hi> of the Means how a man might be Regenerated, and born anew: <hi>Is it poſſible,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nichodemus, that a man can return again into his Mothers Womb?</hi> Did Jeſus Chriſt anſwer this demand, by affirming that in the holy Sacrament of Baptiſm, the water was converted into the body, into Fleſh and Blood, and tranſubſtantiated in a carnal womb, to be there again ingendered, and regenerate? Was there not alſo as great reaſon, according to your Magick, to have returned this anſwer, as well as in the holy Sacrament of the Supper? For the one of theſe Sacraments ſignifies Regeneration, the other Nouriſhment. Now Regeneration is as admirable to humane Wiſdom, as Nouriſhment; for conformable to humane and carnal Judgment it may ſeem impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that we can be twice engendered and begotten. But our good God uſeth the like Interpretation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, as of the Communion of his Fleſh and Blood; which is, that theſe Sacramental terms muſt be ſpiritually conceived, and not carnally; for the Fleſh profits not, but the Spirit quickens. What is of the Fleſh is carnal, what is of the Spirit, ſpiritual.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:46261:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The holy Apoſtle relating to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> what he had received at Gods hands, admoniſhed them of the coming of Jeſus Chriſt; during the expectation whereof, he commands them to communicate of the body and blood of Jeſus Chriſt, by the fraction of bread, and the Cup of Benediction, called the New Teſtament, and New Covenant, contracted by the blood of Jeſus Chriſt: Wherefore, ſeeing we are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the ſecond coming of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> being aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded up into Heaven, and ſet at the right hand of God the Father; till the day predeſtinated that he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to judge the quick and the dead: How, O ye Papiſts, will ye reconcile this paſſage, when by the Magick you utter; you make him deſcend, and return the body of Jeſus Chriſt in <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>bone,</hi> before the time preordained for his ſecond coming?</p>
            <p>This Magick was by you reſtored, ſince the firſt Author of your Miſſal Sacrifice, <hi>Numa Pompilius;</hi> who by his Magick divulged, that he made his Nymph and Goddeſs <hi>Egeria</hi> come down from Heaven, as alſo his <hi>Jupiter Elicius,</hi> by whoſe means there were ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial ſecrets and Myſteries revealed to him. If by your Magick the round conſecrated Hoſt, was tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated into the true and real body of Jeſus Chriſt, the bread being no more bread, but the true body, how came ye to be ſo preſumptuous, to break and tear in pieces the body of Jeſus Chriſt, according to the invention of <hi>Sergius</hi> the 2d. of that Name, your Predeceſſor <hi>Roman</hi> Pontife? Are not you far more execrable Executioners than your Predeceſſors Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which crucified Jeſus Chriſt, and yet they never tare nor rent his body in pieces, as he Propheſied?</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding you are not contented to have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46261:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>broken it into three pieces, but in your Miſſal Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces you preſume to drown and ſteep one portion in Wine, tranſubſtantiated into blood, to be ſwallowed and drunk.</p>
            <p>To confirm your Magick of Tranſubſtantiation; why took you no order to preſerve from corruption your little round printed Hoſts, which you keep and lay up ſo curiouſly in reliquaries, and boxes, after they are tranſubſtaniated into fleſh, and bone, and into the real body of Jeſus Chriſt? Is it not an abominable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie to believe that the body of Chriſt is capable of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption? Nay, and often times is eaten, by Worms, Weaſels, Rats, and Mice? Can you interpret this, to be an accident without ſubſtance? When your Hoſts become many times ſtinking and corrupted <hi>Cibaries;</hi> many times alſo devoured by bruit beaſts of the Earth, which you cauſe to be burned and their Aſhes laid up in Reliquaries?</p>
            <p>When <hi>Victor</hi> the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of that Name, Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> received Poyſon by your tranſubſtantiated Wine into blood; was this an accident without ſubſtance? or when the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of that Name, was poyſoned, by eating of a little round conſecrated and tranſubſtantiated Hoſt, was it without ſubſtance, when it procured death? There was much more appearance for the celeſtiall Manna, given to the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the which though it corrupted, when it was kept, yet that which was reſerved in ſecret, within the Ark of the Lords covenant was preſerved without corruption; but yet for all this was it tranſubſtantiated into Fleſh, and bones to be called celeſtial bread deſcending from Heaven, the bread of Life, or the bread of Angels?</p>
            <p>Now it remains for us to conteſt with the ſubtil Reaſons of the Prieſts, who to make a foundation for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46261:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>their magick, inſiſt carnally upon the word <hi>Eſt,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that theſe words were expreſly written, <hi>This is my Body, This is my Blood,</hi> when Jeſus Chriſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted the holy Sacrament of his body and his blood, under the Symbols of Bread and Wine. But I deſire all thoſe that are zealous for the honour of God, exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to weigh the ſacred Inſtitution of this Sacrament, by which God meant to ſymbolize and ſignifie the communion of his body by the Bread, and drinking of his blood by the Wine and Cup. All will confeſs that the true and principal nouriſhment of mans body, is comprehended under the kinds of Bread and Wine: ſo that the term of Bread is often taken in the Holy Scriptures for the nouriſhment and life of man.</p>
            <p>Let us enter into an Examination of the paſſages of the Bible. Was not the firſt Man, created after Gods ſimilitude, for the penalty of his offence, told, that he ſhould eat his bread with the ſweat and labour of his body? Can any man be ſo ignorant as not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that this was underſtood by the living and life of man? When <hi>Jacob</hi> prayed unto God to give him bread and raiment, did not he underſtand by Bread whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was requiſite for his whole nouriſhment? when we hear recited, that God rained bread upon the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> being in the Deſert, and that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were repleniſhed with this celeſtial bread; this term of bread was it not conceived by the Celeſtial Manna ſent by God to ſuſtain the People of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Is this Manna call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the bread of Heaven, and the bread of Angels, given to the People without labour or travel?</p>
            <p>When <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> meant to furniſh good Father <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Army, did he not preſent him with Bread and Wine?</p>
            <p>When <hi>Abraham</hi> was to gratifye and refreſh three
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46261:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Angels that appeared unto him, did he not expoſe unto them bread baked upon the Embers? Did not he give <hi>Agar</hi> Bread for her nouriſhment? <hi>Iſaacs</hi> mother to favour her beſt beloved ſon, gave him bread. <hi>Joſeph</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> offered Bread to his Brethren for their nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>When we go about to deſcribe a Famine and ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Victual, do we not ſay, there wants bread? when God promiſed any mercy or favour to his people that did keep his Commandments, did he not give them an aſſurance of Bread in ſufficiency? when he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends unto us the poor, as his members, commands he us not to give them bread? Its bread therefore which nouriſheth and ſatisfieth the heart and life of man.</p>
            <p>When Satan enterpriſed to tempt Jeſus Chriſt to teſtifie that he was true Man; did not he make choice of Bread, when he invited him to make the ſtones bread?</p>
            <p>When Jeſus Chriſt celebrated his Banquets to give bodily nouriſhment, once to 5000 men, and then again to 4000 perſons, did he not ſhew his power under the Symbol of bread? when he taught us to addreſs our prayers to God, did he not expreſly ordain in the Lords Prayer, that we ſhould requeſt of God to give us our daily Bread? and Bread is not only mentioned in the Holy Scriptures for vulgar and corporal nouriſhment, but alſo in Sacrifices celebrated by the Hebrew Prieſts, and the preſcript Law of Sacred Bread ordained by God, that was Azimal bread without Leaven, other Bread was termed the Bread of propoſition, which the Prieſts every week renewed and eat, which <hi>David</hi> uſed, preſented to him by <hi>Achimilech</hi> the high Prieſt.</p>
            <p>Contrariwiſe the term of bread, (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.) is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the Bread of iniquity, of Lies, of Sorrow,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46261:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>to polluted bread of Idolaters, to bread of Coinquination offered upon the Altar; to bread of Mourning, and to bread of Trembling. The <hi>Ephramites</hi> alſo called Aſhy and unturned Loaves, that is to ſay, half-baked, half circumciſed, and Idolaters.</p>
            <p>And therefore, O ye Popiſh <hi>Capernaites,</hi> you muſt not be ſo obdurate and inveterate in your Carnalities, as not to obſerve the Phraſes of the Holy Scripture, in which bread is oftentimes taken for Terreſtrial and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal bread; as when it was ſaid, that Man did not live by bread alone, but alſo by whatſoever proceeded out of the Mouth of God.</p>
            <p>Sometimes alſo bread is taken for the Word of God, &amp; Doctrin: when Jeſus Chriſt commanded his Apoſtles from eating Leavened bread with the <hi>Phariſees;</hi> theſe terms of bread and leaven, are they not expreſſed by the Doctrin of the Heretical <hi>Phariſees?</hi> when the <hi>Canaani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Woman demanded Grace &amp; Mercy for her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters health, detained in a long Malady of ſickneſs; did not Jeſus Chriſt anſwer her, how it was not lawful to take the Childrens bread, and to caſt it to Dogs? Was not the bread in this anſwer taken for Life and Health, and not only for Corporal nouriſhment? Wherefore if bread is taken for the Life of Man, which depends prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally upon bread and wine, and that Gods goodneſs, accommodating it ſelf to our infirmities, made choice of theſe two Signs and Symbols, or notable marks, to ſignifie his Body or his Blood; that is to ſay, the bread, and the wine, theſe two Proviſions being common to all Nations, was this any reaſon, to build upon it a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Tranſubſtantiation, as if God without it were not mighty enough, really to figure, and repreſent unto us Sacramentally, that Life was given us: Yea, Life E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, by the Communion of conſecrated bread and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46261:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>wine of benediction; theſe being Figures and Symbols of his Body, and of his Blood?</p>
            <p>Jeſus Chriſt produced theſe words, that the bread is his Body, and the wine is his Blood; he alſo ſaid, that himſelf was the bread of Life, the living bread, and that he was the living bread come down from Heaven. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſays, that he who eats of that bread ſhall live eternally: Doth this infer by the word <hi>Eſt,</hi> that Jeſus Chriſt is converted and tranſubſtantiated into bread, and that he is no more Chriſt, but an accident without ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. O abominable Hereſies! have you any more reaſon, Oh you Obdurate-Popiſh Prieſts, to interpret theſe words carnally: <hi>This is my Body,</hi> to tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate the bread into the Body, than when he teſtifies, that himſelf was the bread, to tranſubſtantiate him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bread, conſidering that it is written, how the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of this bread gives Eternal Life? Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> he alſo ſays of himſelf; <hi>Hic eſt panis qui de caelo deſcendit,</hi> in both theſe places, is not this word <hi>eſt</hi> uſed? and yet muſt we needs hereupon infer that tranſubſtantiation, inſtead of Orthodoxly interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame by Metonymy, a familiar compariſon of bread to Jeſus Chriſt, that we might apprehend how Eternal Life was given us by him, and likewiſe by him our ſpiritual Food is Miniſtred; even as by bread a nouriſhment corporal?</p>
            <p>Howſoever we muſt allwayes have recourſe to the true expreſſion of Jeſus Chriſt, the abſolute Law-giver, and Author of this holy Sacrament; who expounding his own inſtitution ſaith in the firſt place, that he is the bread of life, then afterwards he ſayes that his bread is his fleſh, and his body, which muſt be offered for the ſalvation of the world; he ſayed his fleſh is true meat, and his blood true drink, he ſayes, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46261:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>eats of his fleſh, and drinks of his blood, he will remain in him. How doth he himſelf expound this manducation? Jeſus Chriſt his own words expreſſeth himſelf; <hi>Whoſoever comes to me, ſhall never hunger; and he that believes in me, ſhall never thirſt,</hi> (Joh. 6.) Is not this a true eating, and a true drinking, never again to be hungry, nor never to thirſt? muſt not we in this have faith, which conſiſts in Spirit?</p>
            <p>To addreſs our ſelves to Jeſus Chriſt, our celeſtial bread, our ſpiritual drink, wherewith to be ſatisfied for ever, to quench our thirſt of ſin perpetually, muſt we run to the Magick of Tranſubſtantiation, and forge an accident without a ſubſtance? Wherefore, O Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts, do ye preſume to invent any other inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, than that of Jeſus Chriſt, who witneſſeth that the fleſh profiteth nothing; but the Spirit quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens? and that his words are not carnal, but ſpiritual, giving ſpirit and life, by faith and confidence, that he is our Saviour, incarnate, dead, and crucified, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe for us eternal life; and then raiſed up again, he did aſcend into Heaven, ſits at the right hand of God his Father, remaining an eternall Prieſt, Propitiator, Mediator and Redeemer.</p>
            <p>To return to this term, <hi>Eſt,</hi> that does ſo moleſt the Prieſts Brains, that they dream out of it a Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: If Jeſus Chriſt uttered how he was the true Vine, that God his Father was the Keeper, and that we are the Branches; can we hereupon conclude by this word, <hi>Eſt,</hi> a magick of the Tranſubſtantiation of God, into the Keeper of a Vine, of Jeſus Chriſt into a Vine, and of our ſelves into branches?</p>
            <p>If Jeſus Chriſt was ſaid to be the immaculate Lamb that takes away the ſins of the world; (<hi>John</hi> 16.) can we hereupon induce a Tranſubſtantiation? If Jeſus
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46261:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt ſaid, that he was the door of the Sheepfold, by whom we muſt enter to be ſaved; and that he is the good Paſtor, and we his Sheep; muſt we needs ſo ſtrain and wreſt theſe places of the Holy Scripture, as to think it neceſſary, becauſe the word <hi>Eſt</hi> is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to believe a tranſubſtantiation?</p>
            <p>When Jeſus Chriſt admoniſhed his Apoſtles, ſaying, that they were the Salt of the Earth, did he therefore tranſubſtantiate or convert them into Statutes or Pillars of Salt, as he did <hi>Lots</hi> wife?</p>
            <p>If the Holy Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. wrote, that Jeſus Chriſt is the Rock, out of whom came living water, to waſh and purge us from our ſins; muſt we wreſt out of this a tranſmutation of Jeſus Chriſt into a Rock, or a material Stone?</p>
            <p>If the Holy Apoſtle teſtifieth that we are the body of Chriſt, may we by this infer, that we are tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and now no more men, but tranſubſtantiated into an accident without a ſubſtance?</p>
            <p>I readily foreſee, O ye Obdurate Prieſts, that ye will object all theſe prealledged Places, wherein this word <hi>Eſt</hi> is, and make no mention of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which muſt the more exactly be obſerved, in that theſe be ſacred Myſteries ordained of God, which is moſt true.</p>
            <p>And this word <hi>Eſt</hi> is not found only in the Holy Scriptures formerly cited; but when we ſpeak of Holy Sacraments firſt inſtituted by God for his People <hi>Iſrael;</hi> it is written, that circumciſion is Gods alliance and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant?</p>
            <p>In the Sacrament of the Communion of the Paſchal Lamb, was it ſaid that the Lamb was the Paſſover, which is to ſay the paſſage? but ſhall we induce here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a magick of Tranſubſtantiation? will not you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46261:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>O obdurate Tranſubſtantiators, that in theſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the Holy Scriptures, ſpeaking of Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, that this word <hi>Eſt,</hi> cannot be otherwiſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, than to ſignifie ſome real performance, and that Circumciſion was a ſign and a mark of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and alliance contracted by God with <hi>Abraham;</hi> the Paſchal Lamb was alſo a Sacred Sign of the Paſſage, for a remembrance of their delivery out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> The Ark of alliance for another Sacrament, of which it is written, That <hi>it is the Truth and Power of the Lord;</hi> muſt we underſtand by this, that it was tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated into the real Majeſty of God? We muſt, we muſt, I ſay, interpret the holy Scriptures with diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in humility and ſincerity, without ſophiſticati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and without Magick, ſoundly to apprehend the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of words, and not ſtick ſo cloſe to the Letter, which kills; but receive the word of God in lively ſpirit.</p>
            <p>If then the ſacred Ark is called the Lord, and Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated God, becauſe in it he exerciſed his omnipotent power, and declared his Oracles and Myſteries by exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ſigns, to draw the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> people to be mindfull of God, and to fear and obey him: If Jeſus Chriſt ſaid alſo, that he is Bread that came down from Heaven, the bread of Life, and the Wine was his Blood; that the Cup is the New Teſtament; by the External ſigns of Bread and Wine, to give us to underſtand, that our life and ſaving Nutriment depended only on Jeſus Chriſt, and that by his Death and Blood hed we have aſſurance of eternal Life, even as Bread and Wine ſerve for corporal nouriſhment, and that he meant and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained theſe ſacred ſigns, to be to us for Sacraments to approve and confirm our Faith; did he determine we ſhould hereby <hi>Capernize</hi> and <hi>Nicodemize,</hi> to enquire or make doubt of God's power, how it is poſſible to eat
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46261:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Body, or drink the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt? How we can poſſibly be born anew? ſeeing the promiſe was made unto us by the word, wherefore, O ye blind Prieſts of the popiſh Idolatry, have ye conceived a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal tranſubſtantiation, diſtruſting in the incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible power of God? May it not ſuffice you ſimply to believe, that the body and blood of Jeſus Chriſt was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and Sacramentally offered, to communicate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for our ſpiritual nouriſhment the Bread, being truly his body, and the Wine his blood, to the faith of the worthy receiver, which we muſt worthily receive by faith, and purity of conſcience, as ſacred ſigns and marks of the Divine character, without ſearching too ſubtilly after the means, other than the plain interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Jeſus Chriſt, that the fleſh profits not, but the Spirit quickens, that his words are Spirit and life? Should we doubt whether God hath power by the Symbols of Bread and Wine conſecrated, to make us communicate of the body and blood of Jeſus Chriſt, though the bread remain bread, and the Wine wine? if it were otherwiſe, this could be no Sacrament, but rather called a Miracle, as when Jeſus Chriſt converted the Water into Wine, he then uſed the Miracle of tranſubſtantiation, changing the water into wine; but he ordained not this for a Sacrament, as he did the communion of his body and blood, by the ſacred figures of bread and wine.</p>
            <p>Was it not alſo as eaſie for God to change the wine into blood, or the bread into fleſh, as for <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> to change the water of the River into blood to confirm the hardneſs of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart; or when the clouds were turned into the fleſh of <hi>Quailes,</hi> that rained upon the people of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Nevertheleſs, God did not ordain that theſe Miracles ſhould ſerve for ordinary Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46261:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>but herein he applyed himſelf to our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, exhibiting to us Sacred but not Tranſubſtantiated ſigns, and yet are not vain or fantaſtical; but ſigns external, that we may Behold, Touch, Eat, and Taſt, remaining ſtill in their ſubſtance: and nevertheleſs they repreſent Sacramentally what is by them compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and intimated, wherein conſiſts the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our faith, to manifeſt by a Sacramental work and Miniſtration, that we are in the number of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, and ſuſtained by the holy Sacraments of Baptiſm and the Supper.</p>
            <p>And further I would leave with you, for your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confutation in this Horrid Hereſie of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, this apt Similitude of the Sun; ſeeing by ſome Apoſtles, Chriſt is called the Sun of Righteouſneſs, to whom the Son may not unfitly be compared, becauſe Light comes down from Heaven by this luminous and glorious ſpherical Planet; and ſo ſpiritual Light is exhibited to us by Jeſus Chriſt, who out of the night and darkneſs of Sin hath brought us into the brightneſs and clear Sun-ſhine of of his Grace. You may now therefore underſtand, carnal and groſs <hi>Capernaites,</hi> this ſufficient and evident compariſon, to intimate that the Infinite power of God is much more compleat and perfect, than your abominable invention of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</p>
            <p>Will you not acknowledg, except your Eyes be blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and obfuſcated with the palpable darkneſs of Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, that the Sun gives us his light, his force, his heat and vigor, and yet nevertheleſs, the Body it ſelf of the Planetal Sun remains &amp; continues in his Spherical Orb? Do you not uſe to ſay in ordinary common Language, when the Window of an Houſe is open on that part where the Sun ſhines, that the Sun is come into the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46261:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Houſe, although the Sun remains ſtill in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Muſt we therefore hale and violently pull the Body of the Sun, to make it deſcend, and be tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated into this Earthly ſubſtance, before it can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford its heat, beams, light and nouriſhment to Plants, Trees, Herbs, and Beaſts of the earth? are you ſo bruitiſh, O <hi>Capernaites!</hi> as not to recognize, that the true Sun of Righteouſneſs Jeſus Chriſt, hath more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than this Aſtral Sun, being but Mortal and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated?</p>
            <p>If then a Mortal Creature hath this power to infuſe into us the virtue and efficacy of his Body by his Beams, Light and Heat extend really and effectually over the whole Earth, the Body remaining ſtill in its Heaven; and ſhall we not believe that God an immortal Creator hath much more power to grant unto us the true Sun of Righteouſneſs Jeſus Chriſt, to give us the virtue and power of his Body and Blood ſhed for us by the beams, light, and heat of his Holy Spirit, except he be by your Magick plucked from the right hand of God, and his Body drawn out of Heaven, to be tranſubſtantiated up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth? Why ſhould not Jeſus Chriſt have this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to afford us his light, and to offer his Body and Blood to enter into us, if by Faith and a pure Conſcience we be ready to receive him, by the efficacy of his Holy Spirit, as well and much better than the Spherical Sun can enter into our Houſes with his force and power, and never be drawn out of its Heaven, to be tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated?</p>
            <p>The Sun is an entire Body created, reſiding in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the cauſe of the generation of Plants, Trees, and Herbs, which by its force and calidity, gives ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to whatſoever lives upon the Earth, and in one and the ſame moment, hath power to quicken, heat, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46261:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>nouriſh an infinite number of Plants, Trees, and Beaſts of the Earth; and yet his Body is never ſeparated, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, drawn out of his Sphere, nor tranſubſtantiated. The Body alſo of Jeſus Chriſt which he aſſumed up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven, ſet at the right hand of God; hath not that more force, more virtue, more power, to regenerate, nouriſh, and ſuſtain us; to give us his virtue, light, and beams; to inſpire, quicken, illuminate and nouriſh us, and in a moment to make us all by Faith partakers of his Body and Blood; to make us his Members, united in and by him, through his true promiſe, comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under the Symbols and ſacred Signs commended to us, till the ſecond coming of his humanity be revealed upon Earth?</p>
            <p>Wherefore then, O ye Popiſh Prieſts, have you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed this Magick of tranſubſtantiation, to blaſpheme againſt God, to impair his Omnipotency, and diſable his virtue more than you do that of the Spherical Sun, but his Creature?</p>
            <p>Thus do I conclude, praying that God would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to open their blind Eyes, if it may be; but becauſe they are wilfully blind and ſee not, becauſe they will not ſee; O Lord, if thou wilt not turn them, for the good of thy Church, and for the glory of thy Power, overturn them, and haſten their utter fall, and Eternal overthrow.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46261:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
